All right.
And we're just starting the meeting here.
Gonna admit everybody online might just
take a minute.
And thank you, Johnny.
And just as a reminder to everyone,
this is Dominic from the Department of
Health.
I'd like to invite you to the Propagation
Committee meeting.
We are doing a hybrid meeting today.
So we have about 20 people in the room
with us.
And then I can't,
I'm actually not looking at the meeting,
but we have probably about 15 or so
online so far.
And so just as a reminder to everyone,
we do have most of the visuals off
because of bandwidth issues so that we
can ensure that people who are in areas
of the state and don't have as good
bandwidth as some of the other areas are
not dropping off and having to log back
in as much as possible.
And then the other thing to remind
everyone is we are reporting this meeting.
And so Please remember to keep your
language appropriate.
And that is actually the other reason why
we left the video off,
so we do not have to edit the video more
than necessary to post it online.
With that,
I will turn it on over to Chris Pisgussky,
the chair.
And Chris, here you go.
Thank you, Dominic.
So as many of you know,
I'd like to start these meetings off with
30 seconds of silence.
Just a little ritual to bring a little
compassion to a Whirlpool of chaos and to
remind ourselves why we're in this work.
So bear with me.
Thank you, everyone.
OK, all right, thank you everyone.
Next we'll go into introductions.
I'm going to start with introductions
online today.
So we did them in first and last time.
Remember,
if you if we end up voting on something,
you must have introduced yourself to have
a voting share.
So please just tell us who you are if
you're from New Mexico and any
affiliations you have.
All right,
looks like we've got one hand up in the
chat.
John Eslick.
I have enabled your mic.
You can talk when ready.
Hi, my name is John, John Eslick.
I'm a local home mycologist.
I'm I've done work with Four Corners
fungi and New Mexico fungi.
I'm just here to help any way that I can.
Awesome.
Thank you, John.
And next we have James Brown.
James, I have enabled your mic.
You can talk when ready.
Afternoon, Chris.
And thank you again for sharing this
committee.
Everybody else,
hope you're having a great afternoon in
New Mexico.
My name is James Brown,
the doctor of pharmacy here in New Mexico.
I'm out of Albuquerque.
I'm psilocybin trained as well as
representing 5° N healing foundation.
It's a non profit and we're hoping to
just provide whatever you guys knowledge,
information sharing.
It's just important that we all come
together in this space.
Remember,
you know that this is for the individual
and that we're all here together.
Thank you, Chris.
Thanks James.
Next we have James Fergera.
James, whoops.
Let's see.
I have enabled your mic.
You can talk when ready.
Everybody.
James Ferreira with Ignites energy and
I'm a resident of Taharis, New Mexico.
Awesome.
Thanks, James.
And then we have Hannah Rose.
Hannah, I have enabled your mic.
You can talk when ready.
And this is a reminder of the mic icon in
teams is up at the top right hand side.
You'll just want to click on that.
There you go.
Thank you.
Hello.
Nice to see everyone.
My name is Hana Rose.
I am here in Silver City, NM.
I'm a BSW student in the social work
program that Western New Mexico and the
first generation codendetta and trained
in psilocybin administration and
facilitation and just really glad to be
here today with all of you.
Thank you, Hannah.
All right.
And I think that the last hand up that I
saw,
let me just double check the chat here.
Let's see.
OK.
Catherine Sanchez, Bureau chief,
New Mexico workers compensation,
medical cost containment.
Good to have you, Catherine.
All right,
And now we're going to introduce folks
around the room.
Tom Starr, New Mexico citizen.
I own Santa Fe Mountain mushrooms here in
Santa Fe.
Long time resident and excited to be here.
Hi everyone, my name is Denali Wilson.
I'm the state director of strategic
support for the Healing Advocacy Fund,
which is a nonprofit that supports state
regulated access programs for psilocybin
like ours here in New Mexico.
I'm normally based in Las Cruces,
so happy to be here in Santa Fe.
Hello, my name is Zachary Luhan.
I'm the owner of of Meadow City Mushrooms
in Vegas, New Mexico.
I'm a generational New Mexican and more
than 10 generations.
Hello,
my name is Eric Baca and I'm a New Mexico
resi.
Hey,
James Blackford here with my wife Kat out
of Clovis, NM.
Super excited about everything
everybody's doing.
And yeah, so awesome.
I'm Gregory Evans.
I'm an independent researcher and home
mycologist.
No affiliations.
Santa Fe resident.
Eyes off the wall speed in the apartment.
Fired as the senior compliance officer
for the medical suicide movement.
I'm Kamala Kirke Cyrus Rotman.
I'm the associate environmental scientist
for the and I'm also my name is Ismail
Zuta.
I'm one of the health educators for the
Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin.
So as you can talk from the accent
actually originally from the UK,
but now based in Santa Fe, Apia,
Jerry IT project manager and I'm not a
trucker with a medical and good afternoon
everyone.
I'm Dominic Zerlo.
I'm the center director for medical
cannabis and psilocybin.
Hello everyone, good afternoon.
Jorge Gonzalez,
medical psilocybin program manager.
I'm Skye Rivers.
I'm with the Santa Fe Report,
and then we got one more online.
Eric Barlow lives in Las Cruces and no
affiliations.
Oh,
and I'm Johnny Mache with the department.
Thank you, Johnny.
OK,
so next we're going to go over the next
set of draft rules that Department of
Health is set up.
I believe we're displaying them now.
So it's the disciplinary actions and
appeals process.
I'm going to turn it over to Dominic
since he seemingly likes to read these
things.
And just to check for everybody online,
can you see the draft on your screen?
If so, just you can just thumbs up.
OK, cool.
I'm seeing thumbs up.
We're good.
Hey, good afternoon everyone.
Before I actually start going into the
draft to sort of review this section or
sections,
I just wanted to go over a little bit of
what's going to be happening as far as
next steps.
So we have an internal deadline that we
are hoping to be able to publish the
whole set of rules for public review and
public comment by March 24th,
which is just next week.
So we're,
we've been working on it quite a bit and
between the parts that we did last week
in the meeting and this week,
it's about 30% of the rules that we're
actually,
we've actually been going through in here.
Once we actually publish it for the in
the notice in the New Mexico Register and
in the Albuquerque Journal,
it will be posted on our website and that
link will be there.
We'll do an announcement on the main
psilocybin page linking to it so that
people can read through the entire draft
for these rules.
Then there's 30 days where it's open for
public comment.
So please go and read it, look and see,
find what typos we made, you know,
see what other potential issues concerns
that there may be and provide it back to
us.
So for example,
last week we had a couple of questions on
clarification.
For example, in part of it,
there was a request to clarify what type
of registration someone needed to have
for the Secretary of State for taxing
revenue.
So we clarify that language a little bit,
things like that that came out in last
week's meeting and some questions,
concerns that we also have taken to
address.
So please don't hesitate to do that.
And then at that point,
so long as we make our internal deadline,
which I'm positive we will,
then the rule hearing itself will be
scheduled for April 24th.
Now that is with the caveat,
if we don't make our internal deadline,
those dates will be pushed back and we'll
of course announce those.
But I'm pretty confident that we're going
to make stuff.
But in any case,
I just wanted to make sure that we have
that aspect that people understood.
Now,
the rule hearing itself will be a hybrid
meeting as well.
It will be at the Runnels building,
which is at 1190 S Saint Francis here in
Santa Fe.
And so if anyone wants to come in person,
please do.
We will also have the online virtual
version that will be happening
simultaneously.
So if people have comments that they want
to make, they can do that.
The other aspect is you can also submit
written comments.
Now that will actually go directly to our
legal, our legal department.
And so there'll be a specific address
that that needs to go to.
We will have that as well.
That'll be a part of the announcement of
the rule hearing itself.
So just make sure to go to that look to
see on that.
That is the one thing because that's a
part of the legal process that doesn't go
to the medical dot psilocybin e-mail
address that many of you are used to.
So just be aware of that.
And at this point are there any questions
with regard to the process?
John, don't be sorry.
I want questions.
Questions are good.
I was curious,
you said in the last meeting and this
meeting together that will amount for
approximately 30% of the rules,
so that the 70% of the rules that will be
those will just come out when you and be
open and be open for comment.
OK, cool.
I just want to make sure that there's a
30% between these two.
The other 70% will will read them.
All right, OK, right.
And again,
part of the reason for doing that is,
you know, quite frankly,
after the recommendations were made,
we could have just gone ahead with doing
the rule hearing itself.
But we wanted to provide some examples of
what,
what what they would look like so that
people could have an idea to look at them
and have a little bit of a preview now.
So the section I'm going through has that
caveat just like last week that if we get
suggestions here today that it's like, oh,
we need to clarify that it may look a
little different when you see the
published online version because we are,
that's why we're here.
We want to get feedback,
we want to understand, to know.
And so that's a part of the idea.
Normally in the rule making process,
it's not actually shown to the public
until that actual publication date and
then everybody has it.
So we wanted to make sure we had a
significant amount.
And so that's why we kind of said let's
do these couple sections kind of give an
idea of difference.
I hope that helps.
The other thing just to,
as I mentioned for especially for those
who are in the room,
if you have questions and you take the
mic,
please just remind everybody because
especially online,
they don't necessarily know who's
speaking.
Just remember to say your name again,
just so that they know.
And I have to remember that myself.
So that's a reminder to myself as much as
anyone else.
But any other questions either in the
room or online?
I just want to take a second to echo what
Dominic said.
Please bring your voice into the space.
We need everybody to make this a good
program.
So I encourage you all to be your most
courageous selves and step up if you
think something needs to be said in this
meeting.
OK, I don't see anything online,
so we'll go on ahead.
So this is the disciplinary actions and
appeal process section.
And so just to give everybody a little
bit of an idea of this is if for example,
during an inspection visit or a
compliance visit,
we were to go into a production facility
and there was some sort of an issue.
And so we've done a notice of non
compliance people the the entity will
have had the time to correct it.
So for example,
say if it was something like there were
cleaning solutions that were left out,
we'd give them written notice and they
would have 30 days,
business days or I'm sorry,
calendar days to correct that potential
issue.
And so this is if it is not corrected or
if there is a severe issue that would be
problematic for potential health and
safety, this is then those next steps.
So just so everybody knows,
there is a section that does talk about
that monitoring and if a correction act
corrective action is needed.
And it,
and we didn't include that in because
that's really just if you have an action
or if there is an issue,
you're given 30 days to correct it.
And then if it's not corrected,
here's kind of the next steps.
And we wanted to show this especially
because, you know,
we're here to try to assist and help,
not to try to punish.
And so we want to make sure everybody
understood there's an entire due process
before other items are going to happen.
And of course,
this is with the immediate potential or
that there is the immediate potential.
If there was something that really would
be deemed potentially problematic for
health and safety of patients or staff or
any of anything like that, for example,
big giant holes in the floor that people
can trip and fall into like that sort of
a thing.
But even there you would have the option
and ability to correct that within the 30
days.
That makes sense.
OK,
so and I'm going to read through and
we'll do section by section.
But please,
if anybody has questions as they go
through online,
put your hand on up or in the room,
put your hand on up and that's not a
problem.
We will interrupt.
Don't worry about.
Well, he keeps on talking, That's OK,
Make me shut up.
That's perfectly fine.
So disciplinary actions and appeal
process.
A immediate suspension record review
process.
If immediate action is necessary to
protect the health and safety of the
public,
the program administrator or their
designee may be immediately suspend the
permit of a producer or laboratory in
whole or in part.
1A Permittee whose permit has been in
immediately suspended in whole or in part,
may request a record review in accordance
with this Part 2.
The sole issue at a record review on a
summary suspension is whether the permit
shall remain suspended pending a final
adjudicary hearing and subsequent
decision by the Secretary.
3A permittee given notice of summary
suspension may submit a written request
for a record review.
To be effective,
the written request shall a be made no
later than 30 calendar days from the date
of the notice issued by the department
and is determined by the postmark.
B be properly addressed to the medical
psilocybin program.
C state the requester's name, address,
and telephone number,
B provide a brief narrative rebutting the
circumstances of the suspension or
withdrawal,
and B include attachments of any
additional documentation that the
permittee wishes to be considered in the
record review.
Was there any questions?
So Demali,
this is Denali from healing advocacy find.
I just want to make the recommendation
that you consider increasing the time for
response to 60 days,
especially for parties that are pro SE
that might not have legal counsel.
30 days is just not a lot of time to
assemble the, the enumerated things,
especially if somebody is not operating
with legal counsel and then you know the
the opportunity to find an attorney if
they want to.
I just would recommend a little bit more
time.
Thank you.
Denali other questions or comments and
just as a reminder, online,
if you would like to comment,
you can raise your hand with the raise
icon that's up at the top left part of
the bar in Teams.
OK,
so 4 The record review requested
subsequent to an immediate suspension
shall be conducted by the program
administrator or their designee.
The program administrator shall appoint A
designee to conduct the record review.
By reviewing all documents submitted by
the permittee and the department that are
relative or I'm sorry,
that are relevant to the immediate
suspension.
6 The record review shall be completed
and a written decision issued by the
program administrator or their designee
no later than 15 calendar days from the
date that the medical Psilocybin program
receives the written request for record
review.
The decision shall be issued to the
permittee via certified U.S.
Postal mail.
And just so that people know,
the main reason why things like that are
submitted by mail is just because that
makes it part of the legal record.
And so,
and that's just the main reason for that.
In case one people are wondering, well,
why don't you just send an e-mail?
Emails too often can go to spam or junk
folders and things like that.
We want to ensure people are receiving
those types of notices.
Any questions so far and I'm giving pause
just because I want to make sure that
people have time to digest.
It looks like you've got one hand online,
James Brown and I think your mic is
enabled,
so you should be good talk when ready.
Tomic,
just a couple questions on this one.
Would that be a certified or uncertified
response?
Second question is,
are those only generated through the
inspection process as far as like when
you guys the Department of Health would
show up inspection process or are those
claims also generated through a a,
a complaint through the DoH type of thing?
Can you explain more?
Sure, thank you, James.
And it is certified mail.
So just to clarify that part.
And it is possible that, for example,
if a complaint comes in,
that would actually then trigger a site
visit.
And so this would happen then potentially
after that site visit, but it would be,
there would be a site visit prior to any
sort of a, an issuance of,
of suspension or anything like that.
So this says this is in, oh, sorry,
this is Chris.
This says this is an immediate suspension.
So this wouldn't be part of that.
Like we found out something bad with a, a,
an inspection that we can take time to
remediate.
This is,
this seems to me that this is like
egregious and perhaps the most egregious
thing I can think of is somebody adding
adulterants to product.
This would be an immediate suspension and
I'm assuming there would be a recall of
product.
Yeah, great question, Chris.
And this is Dominic again.
Yeah,
that's why the other portion as far As
for 30 days would be if there's minor
issues,
issues that aren't an immediate concern
to the public health and safety of
patients and staff.
This is really,
if it's an immediate issue and A and as
you said, an egregious issue,
that's how when this whole process would
actually come into.
Yeah, Other questions, Denali,
this is Denali Wilson again.
OK,
I just want to make sure I'm
understanding.
So Section A is 1 type of department
action separate from the rest or these
these are steps.
Section AA is immediate suspension,
which is one class of action.
So this is the set of steps.
So if there was an immediate suspension
due to an egregious public health or
safety risk,
then these are all the steps that would
happen.
And so essentially they,
the permittee would be suspended.
We give them notice,
they then can turn around and request the
record review.
So that's essentially their appeal
process to say we should not be suspended.
And then it's through that review that
the process occurs.
And if the review occurs and it says,
Nope, the suspension needs to continue,
then that's what happens in,
in bullet board.
And then that's that process.
OK.
The, the,
so the reason that I'm asking is in, in .
6.
So there's an opportunity for the program
administrator.
Well,
the program administrator will review the
review,
which we're calling an appeal and issue a
decision.
I I'm just, I'm wondering if there right,
So if I think this is promised on the,
the assumption that there wouldn't be
contradictory evidence submitted because
it if there, if there was,
the department would want to preserve a
way to amend the suspension or repeal the
suspension.
Does that make sense?
Right.
So say, and this is Dominic.
So say, for example,
they had received their notice saying you
have to correct these actions within 30
days, but due to public health issues,
we are doing a suspension until they're
corrected.
That's where they have that time to
submit that document showing for
documentation showing the issue has been
completed, has been fixed,
has been resolved.
And that would be where,
when the record review occurs,
it's a decision of whether or not the
suspension would continue or be lifted.
OK.
And that's, yeah.
And that's what would be, yeah,
that's what would be delivered within 15
calendars.
Day is either we move on to step B or we
remove the we're we're rescinding the
suspension, correct.
OK, got it.
Does that help?
Yeah, it does.
Thank you.
Any questions online?
We've got one in the chat from James
Brown.
Is there a separate form used for
inspections and their findings?
So good question, James.
Yes,
there will be a separate form that will
be that will be done for inspections that
will actually then outline what all the
details and what's expected during an an
inspection is done.
But that's not a part of the rule itself.
The requirements of what a of what a
producer will have to do is a part of the
rule,
but the form in and of itself isn't
necessarily a part of the rule.
But we will have that available prior to
any inspections occur so that people know
and understand what those will look like.
And if we do have in one of the other
sections that we're not showing at the
moment,
it does actually say that based on a form
provided by the department.
So that way people know in advance.
Sky Rivers with the reporter.
So if somebody gets a violation,
is there a two strike,
three strike on record where after a
certain amount they are for the program
business not at this time.
It's really about corrective action.
And so the 30 days to be able to correct
that and then if their issues do con
continue,
there could be potential suspension,
but it's not a a specified one strike two
strike three strike anything else other
question.
OK, we will move forward.
So the notice of disciplinary action
grounds for disciplinary action.
The department may issue notice of an
immediate suspension and notice of
contemplated disciplinary action to a
permittee.
Notice shall be served upon a permittee's
contact.
Person of record Notice shall be served
via certified U.S.
Postal mail.
A notice shall be deemed to have been
served on the date borne by the return
receipt showing delivery or the last
attempted delivery of the notice or
decision to the addressee or refusal of
the addressee to accept delivery of the
notice or decision.
C Grounds for disciplinary action.
No, that's fine.
This is Denali I, So it's settled in.
I think I understand why I was confused
on section A and I'm gonna make a
recommendation.
So on 3D, which is,
you know of this part of the review
record,
what the permittee can submit in response,
it says right now providing A brief
statement rebutting the circumstances of
the suspension or withdrawal,
I'm going to recommend we add or
demonstrating the remediation of the
grounds for suspension.
So it's clear that that is something that
the permatee can do to because it may be
that they want to concede to yes,
you know,
there was something health wise and we've
addressed it, right?
Am I understanding that right in some of
your question responses that that's
grounds for on suspending, right?
Yes,
that that's actually a part of E the
include additional attachments,
but we can add that in as far as clarify.
Yeah, yeah, I,
I would recommend adding it just because
I, I think it's,
it's likely that a lot of people at least
in this first stage of department action
are going to be engaged,
not engaging per SE without the the
support of a lawyer.
It's just helpful to to lay out to people
what they can, what they can list.
And it doesn't seem clear here that.
Right?
Yeah, I mean, the circumstance,
it may be that there is rebuttable
evidence of whatever the department found,
but we want to invite people to fix the
problem, too.
Thank you.
We'll pass that on.
Any other questions?
OK.
See grounds for disciplinary action.
Disciplinary action may be taken against
a permittee or or permit applicant.
Disciplinary action may consist of
revocation or suspension in whole or in
part permit,
denial of an application for a permit,
and other actions.
Disciplinary action may be imposed based
on a violation of any provision of this
rule.
B Selling or distributing psilocybin or
psilocybin product in a manner that is
inconsistent with rule or statute.
C Threatening or harming a patient,
practitioner, clinician, guide,
or an employee of the department.
B Intentionally destroying, damaging,
altering, removing,
or concealing evidence of a violation of
ruler statute.
Attempting to do so or asking or
encouraging another person to do so.
E Conduct.
Conduct that shows willful, willful,
or reckless disregard for health and
safety.
F Failure to comply with the Department's
requested access to premises or materials.
G Falsification or misrepresentation of
any material or information submitted to
the department.
H Failure to adhere to any attestation,
acknowledgement, verification,
or other representation made to the
department.
I Failure to submit or disclose
information required by this rule or
otherwise requested by the department.
J Failure to correct any violation of
this rule that is cited as a result of a
review or audit of financial records or
other materials or that is cited as a
result of a monitoring visit or site
inspection.
KA Discrepancy between a chain of custody
form and the transported psilocybin
product.
LA finding of non compliance with tax
obligations by a taxation regulatory
authority and MA finding by the
department that any person holds an
ownership interest in a permit or
permittee that is nominal or without the
benefits and risk of genuine ownership.
And I'm going to pause there.
I know that's a long list of thou shalt
not do kind of things, but we want to,
again, a lot of them are items that,
you know,
that we want to ensure that the
permittees are doing what they need to do.
And I know we have a question here in the
book James Blackboard here.
I assume things like a chain of custody
form are going to be standardized and and
we'll have access to and all that stuff.
Yeah, good question, James.
Yes.
And that's actually we had covered that
in another section where that chain of
custody will be determined by the
department.
So it'll be standardized.
It'll actually be electronic and then
printable so that the person who's
actually transferring has a copy of it or
can access a copy of it if necessary,
for example,
if they aren't using an electronic device,
but it'll also be electronic.
So it'll be in the system showing that
it's transferring from one end.
OK.
And then as far as that goes,
I do have some questions as far as like
transferring, you know,
from one permit holder to another,
you know,
end product and that sort of thing.
I know there had been a lot of specifics.
I didn't know if that was going to
eventually gotten into or if that's just
going to be in the whole list of all the
100% of the rules.
It's going to be in the whole list of the
rules, OK.
Because I assume that there are going to
be some rules around that, you know,
we can't stop at, you know,
a pizza buffet and a, you know,
and like before we go there to whatever.
So.
OK.
All right.
Cool.
Yeah.
No, exactly.
And it's a good question, James,
and it's one that, you know,
we want to ensure that the product is
secure and safe,
but also that the people transporting it
are safe.
So for example,
in the early days of cannabis,
for example, when because,
and a lot of people don't necessarily
realize this,
but we did not have dispensaries.
In fact, dispensaries were not allowed.
And so everything was done through
delivery methods.
And then there were a few pick up
locations where people could order in
advance and they could just pick it up
from those locations.
But again,
that's going to was going to the patients
directly and patients to go in purchase
and that sort of thing with psilocybin
because it's going really to the
locations of the permit ease for that the
providers rather what really is going to
happen is it limits that amount of
transportation that's going to be a
problem.
And so there are those sort of rules
regulations that will have in place to
help ensure safety.
So like,
you don't want to have on the side of the
van make huge psilocybin mushrooms and
like that sort of thing to make somebody
a target, you know, that kind of thing,
You know,
thinking about what's your safety plan
because there needs to be 1.
So what does happen if somebody,
for example,
stops off at a convenience store to get
gas or at a gas station and, you know,
something occurs,
What are the protocols that follow?
And some of that we're not going to
necessarily regulate,
but we're going to require a plan and it
be if that makes sense.
Yes, yes.
And and so on the same note of of
something potentially happening.
One question I did have as far as
transporting,
I'm assuming that law enforcement
statewide should be aware when this is
happening, but you know,
you get pulled over.
No,
really I'm supposed to have this right.
Like I assume there's going to be certain
things in place showing proof of whatever,
something like that.
So one,
that's why it's a great question and I
have a ready made answer for you.
The first part is that that's why the the
document for the,
for the chain of custody will be able to
be printed so the person can have it.
But the other thing is,
and a lot of people don't realize we have
this currently for law enforcement is
that we actually have a 24/7 on call law
enforcement line for cannabis where if
someone is driving down the road and they
get stopped by a law enforcement officer
and the officer has questions about what
is and is not legal.
And if somebody is actually a member of
the program and therefore able to carry
the amount of cannabis that patients can
have versus the amount of cannabis that a
non patient can have.
Because it's two different things.
Non patients can have up to 2 oz and then
patients can actually have up to 50.
And so if that were to occur that law
enforcement officer calls the line,
we have on call staff who answer that
line 24/7 holidays everything and are
able to answer those questions and verify
someone is in the program.
And we did that.
We've done that actually since the
beginning of the cannabis program.
And so the line is already exists.
So that infrastructure,
because we're just going to add
psilocybin to that,
where then the officers will be able to
call and we publish that number.
And so that if, say, for example,
you're transporting it and a law
enforcement officer stops and they're
like, yeah,
I don't even know anything about the
program,
You can say here is a number we're able
to identify.
We're able to work with law enforcement
to ensure that they know, yes,
this is legitimate and be able to move
forward.
So yes,
we have already thought about those kinds
of protections and have them.
Oh, yeah, I should thank you, Rob.
Doctor Truckner just asked about bringing
up customs.
We, of course,
cannot do anything with regard to the
federal level.
It's only really at the state and only in
the state.
So one of the things is the Border Patrol
and the custom stops are outside of our
jurisdiction technically.
And if you get stopped by a Border Patrol,
there's not much we can do on a state
level because of their federal
jurisdiction.
However,
we still have had where people have gone
through that, like the checkpoint on I-25,
gotten stopped.
And we're usually able to talk with them
about what the program is about.
People in with regard to in the past
being either patients or members of the
program.
And then it's really up to them what they
decide to do.
Sometimes they simply confiscate items.
Sometimes they let people go,
sometimes they have arrested people.
So we don't have any control over that.
So that's always a caveat.
But we will have that included in some of
the educational material.
And it's not a new issue.
It's one we've dealt with regarding
cannabis since the founding of the
cannabis program.
So thank you, Denali.
Hi Denali again on this issue and Border
Patrol.
I think it's one of the reasons being in
Crucis,
you know that it's really important that
we support a diverse grower market,
right that we have folks down South so
that can distribute to providers down
South.
I did have another recommendation back on
Page 1 and I'm going to write these up
and send them so I I just reading this
again.
So if we look at six.
And this is this is on the same issue of
record review the time you know what
happens if somebody doesn't request a
record review,
I think that's what's missing from the
rules.
I assume there might be some defaults,
right?
If you don't,
if you don't meet this 30 day,
I'm recommending 60 days for a record
review.
What happens then?
So when you read six, it's 6 is the,
the department's action is premised on
the record review being requested.
I think you maybe need a section that
explains what happens if it doesn't,
if there's a default or something like
that.
And again,
just going back to my recommendation that
we give people as much time as as is
reasonable.
And I think 30 days is is just not very
many.
Thank you, Denali.
And if you don't mind sending it to us,
as far as the comments, that's great.
I am writing them down as well though,
so thank you.
OK, sorry I got off the pages.
Any other questions so far?
Yeah.
OK.
So D persons and entities who may request
a hearing.
The following persons or entities may
request a hearing to contest an action or
proposed action of the department in
accordance with this rule.
A permittee whose permit has been
immediately suspended or has received a
notice of contemplated action to impose a
disciplinary action.
And two,
a permit applicant whose application is
denied for any reason other than failure
to submit a completed application or
failure to meet a submittal requirement
of this rule.
Any questions on that?
OK.
Section E Timing and content of request
for hearing a permit,
Permit E or permit applicant who wishes
to request a hearing may do so by mailing
a written request for hearing no later
than 30 calendar days and just as a note,
60 days, as per Denali's suggestion.
30 calendar days from the date that the
notice of contemplated action is received,
or in the case of an immediate suspension,
no later than 30 days from the date of
the immediate suspension and again,
if we have that adjustment to 60 days as
Denali has requested the request shell
one,
be properly addressed to the medical
Psilocybin program.
2 be mailed to the Medical Psilocybin
Program via certified U.S.
Postal mail,
return receipt requested to verify
delivery.
3 State the requester's name, address,
telephone number, and four,
include a statement of the issue that the
requester considers relevant to the
review of the action,
and I'll pause there for any questions or
comments.
OK.
Section F Hearing process one.
All hearings held pursuant to this
section shall be conducted by a hearing
officer appointed by the Secretary.
2 Hearing shall be conducted in Santa Fe,
NM, with the consent of the parties,
but or with the consent of the parties in
another location via telephone or via web
video conference.
3 Hearings held pursuant to this section
that concern patients or patient
applicants shall be closed to the public.
Hearings may also be closed in whole or
in part upon the request of a party to
prevent the disclosure of information
that is confidential under applicable law.
4,
The hearing shall be reported at a
minimum by means of sound reproduction.
And I'll pause there.
And just as a note,
the number 3 is really a per SE.
For example,
a patient is saying I should be enrolled
in this program.
I'm having issues with the provider,
they're not supporting me and I have
questions,
concerns and I've been denied ability to
be in the program.
I'd like this to be reviewed.
That's kind of the that example.
That's why it's patient,
patient applicants and why it's closed to
the public to ensure that their privacy
and confidentiality is maintained.
Any questions Denali?
Thanks.
This is Denali.
I so that got to an earlier question I
had is this are we writing the same
appeal process that will be for
cultivator permittee,
facilitator permittee you you mentioned
providers right now this is all the same
process.
OK, Yeah, yeah, thank you.
Would be the other like educational yeah
for example,
if we had a an education right
educational training program would be
able to follow the same processing.
Those labs are included in here because
they're part of the permittees and permit
applications.
But it should it will all be the same
process for any permit.
OK, thank you.
And so with that in mind,
that's part of why the patient part is
important in here.
So say also for example,
and pardon me 'cause I was thinking on
the patient rule when I was giving the
example,
but a more applicable example to this
would be say a patient is gone in they
have received their medication,
but they have a complaint because,
for example,
they believe they were not given the
proper dose or the high enough dose and
that the dosage was not as it should be
through the testing and the label Like
that would be a complaint.
For example,
that kind of a process or a hearing
because it involves a patient complaint
would be,
or at least the portions revolving around
the patient would be considered
confidential and different.
Does that make sense?
I just want to make sure I'm giving a
good example for this particular place.
So in that case,
it involves both the permit E,
so for example,
a production facility and it involves a
patient.
Any other questions?
I know it's a little bit dry.
I can do voices if people want.
Gregory Evans under the remote hearing
options.
I think it the language could be reworked
to protect our residents a little bit
more and take the onus off of the oh,
and maybe just explicitly call out like
that.
Any request for a remote hearing would be
honoured.
I think the disparate residency is a
major issue.
Thank you, guys.
That's actually a part of that.
That's why it says in it that it can be
done or with the consent of the parties
in the other location or via telehealth
or, I'm sorry, via web video.
Yeah.
And and mind you everybody,
just so everybody also understands,
you know,
this is written more in that legal
regulatory language.
There will be,
we'll have like guides and FAQs and
things like that,
which will outline in a little more plain
language.
Because that's the issue is this is not
plain language,
but our guides and the information
that'll go out to people will be ensuring
that it's written in as plain language as
possible.
So that would help cover that, right.
Just that.
Sorry, follow up on that, Denali.
I yeah,
I would agree that I think in the
regulation it could be right.
So it does say with the consent of the
parties.
I,
I don't know what the language would be
right now,
but I agree that for our rural permittees,
it's it would be helpful to have a
guarantee that the department is not
going to withhold their consent for a, a,
a yeah, yeah,
that's what I was going to say is like
even though I know on paper and legalese,
it allows for the department to overrule
in a, in a way that not be equitable.
OK,
I made comment on that and I'll pass that
along.
Any other comments, questions.
OK Scheduling.
Gee Scheduling.
The department shall schedule and hold
the hearing as soon as practical,
provided that the hearing shall not be
held later than 60 calendar days from the
date the department receives the request
for hearing.
The hearing officer may extend the 60
daytime.
Upon motion for good cause shown,
or the parties may extend the 60 daytime.
By mutual agreement.
The department shall issue a notice of
hearing,
which shall include 1A statement of the
location, date and time of the hearing,
2A short and plain statement of the legal
authority under which the hearing is to
be held, and three,
a short and plain statement of the
subject of the year.
Any questions on this?
This is Denali.
I just I'm going to recommend on this
issue of the virtual,
I'm coming back to that, sorry,
but maybe and I will share this by e-mail.
Maybe the language we could consider is
something so on that too.
After this they were practicable.
The Department shall grant a request for
a virtual hearing for any permittee whose
place of registered business is more than
100 miles from Santa Fe,
something like that.
Questions or comments?
Sorry, any other questions or comments?
OK,
I'm going to include the next two
together because this one is very short.
H Presentation of evidence All parties
shall be given the opportunity to present
evidence and argument on all relevant
issues.
I Record of proceeding The record of the
proceedings shall include the following
One.
All pleadings,
motions and intermediate rulings.
2 Evidence and briefs received or
considered.
3A Statement of matters officially
noticed.
4 Offers of proof,
objections and rulings thereon,
5 Proposed findings and conclusions,
and six any findings or decisions
recommended by the hearing officer for
adoption by the Secretary.
Any questions or comments?
OK, Part J reporting.
A party may request a copy of the
reporting of the proceedings.
OK.
I think actually James Brown put his hand
up.
I think for either something in HR,
I let's go to him real quick, right,
James, your mic should be enabled.
Thank you.
Dominic,
on this one that we were just talking
about, I think it's under.
I would that also include experts in that
proceeding.
Is that just kind of we're just already
saying that they can be included or are
we saying that that does that need to be
written at all about any findings from an
expert in the field or there are other
type of thing there?
Thank you.
Yeah, Thank you on that, James.
Yeah, that would be included in this.
That would be included as part of the
evidence.
If it's a written brief, for example,
it would be there.
If it's done in the hearing,
it's of course reported and a part of the
record.
So if it was then done verbally or a
combination of verbal and visuals,
so say for example there were items shown
on the screen for example,
that would be included in as well.
Any other questions or concerns.
OK Procedures and evidence 1A Party may
be represented by a person licensed to
practice law in New Mexico or a non
lawyer representative or may represent
himself or herself.
2 The rules of evidence is applied in the
courts do not apply in these proceedings.
Any relevant evidence shall be admitted.
Irrelevant, immaterial,
or unduly repetitious evidence may be
excluded.
3 The experience, technical competence,
and specialized knowledge of the hearing
officer, the department,
or the department staff may be used in
the evaluation of evidence.
4 An appellate's failure to appear at the
hearing at the date and time noticed for
the hearing shall constitute a default.
This is Denali just really quickly.
So starting on four that you just read
and through the rest of the rules,
it says appellant instead of permit T and
I'm not sure why because we haven't
really we're not in an appeals process.
So my understanding on it, Denali,
is that at this point they are actually
appealing because they're appealing the
notice of contemplated action or the
suspension or revocation.
And so they are going through an appeal
process.
So that's why it is appellant at this
part.
So where is, yeah,
where's the hearing or the decision final?
Where does it become final in the process?
I think that's the point that somebody
and anything after that would be that's
at part P.
Yeah,
which is what why I think that we're not
right.
So in it,
someone can appeal an administrative
decision,
but that decision has to be final.
So there's rules that aren't,
it doesn't seem our anticipated or set
out here, but there's court rules.
So it's either it's this Form 107,
four or 075.
If it's a constitutional issue that
allows someone to appeal an
administrative decision that's final.
I guess it's the finality of it that has
me questioning whether we're technically
in an appeal or not,
but that might be beyond the scope of
this discussion.
I'll pass it on to the department's
attorneys,
but this is actually pretty standard
language as far as utilizing that when
we're doing the hearing offices hearing
hearings with regard to this sort of
complaint for a suspension notice of
contemplative action.
Gregory Evans on #4 here under a the
appellant's failure to appear at the
enemy,
I think we should include a provision for
good cost medical emergency.
So if you could just speak up a little
bit and other than recommending adding a
provision for good cause under failure to
appear, acts of God and whatnot.
Thank you, Greg.
Any other questions, concerns,
comments OK Part L Conduct of proceeding.
Unless the hearing officer determines
that a different procedure is appropriate,
the hearing shall be conducted in
accordance with the procedure set forth
in this rule.
The following procedure shall apply one.
The appellant shall present an opening
statement and the department may present
an opening statement or reserves the
statement until presentation of the
department's case 2.
After the opening statement, if made,
the appellant shall present their case 3.
Upon the conclusion of the appellant's
case,
the department shall present its case 4.
Upon conclusion of the appellee's case,
the appellant may present rebuttal
evidence and five.
After presentation of the evidence by the
parties,
the parties may present closing arguments.
Any questions, comments.
OK Section M Burden of proof.
The appellant shall bear the burden of
establishing by a preponderance of the
evidence that the decision made or
proposed by the department should be
reversed or modified and continuances.
The hearing examiner may grant a
continuance for a good cause shown.
A motion to continue a hearing shall be
made at least 10 calendar days before the
hearing date.
O Telephonic and web video hearings.
One.
Any party requesting that a hearing be
conducted via telephone or web video
conference shall do so no less than 10
days prior to the date of the hearing.
Notice of the hearing shall be given to
all parties and shall include all
necessary telephone numbers or
instructions for access to the web video
conference.
This is Denali.
Maybe this would be a good place if we're
amenable to adding the provision that the
department shall grant, you know,
for equity reasons for our remote
permittees.
I would just recommend the same,
the same language that we considered in E
No F2 Thank you, Denali.
2 The in person presence of some parties
or witnesses at the hearing shall not
prevent the participation of other
parties or witnesses by telephone or web
video conference with prior approval of
the hearing officer.
And I'll pause there for any any
questions or comments up to this.
P Recommendation,
action and final decision one.
The parties may submit briefs,
including proposed findings of fact and
conclusions of law,
for consideration by the hearing officer.
2 No later than 30 calendar days after
the last submission by a party,
the hearing officer shall prepare and
submit to the Secretary a written
recommendation of action to be taken by
the Secretary.
The recommendation may include proposed
findings of facts,
facts and conclusions of law for adoption
by the Secretary and shall propose
sustaining, modifying,
or reversing the action of proposed
action of the department.
Three.
The Secretary shall issue a final written
decision accepting or rejecting the
hearing officer's recommendation in whole
or in part no later than 45 calendar days
after receipt of the hearing officer's
recommendation.
The final decision shall identify the
final action taken.
Service of the Secretary's final decision
shall be made upon the appellant by
certified mail.
The final decision or order shall be
included in a permittees file with the
medical psilocybin program.
And after Greg or any other comments on
this section will allow,
James has a comment on the previous
section, but we can come back to that.
You want to take care of that first,
I just wanted to call out cannabis's 10
day emergency earring window and see if
we could apply something like that.
For a small producer,
being out for 135 days based on five
months is the best.
Let's see,
we'll go to James Brown's question.
Can you explain and expand on the
originations of these types of claims?
Will there be examples of what these
types of complaints can be?
I'm not 100% sure what you mean, James,
but let me attempt and if I'm wrong,
please tell me.
So these would be things, for example,
if we were to go in a site inspection and
where, for example,
there were chemicals that were being
utilized and being sprayed through
misters or something like that.
I'm hard pressed to think of something,
quite frankly,
that really would be egregious,
especially with all the people that I've
met involved in the area.
But and in this.
But if there was something like that that
were happening,
even if it were being done accidentally,
like for example,
bleach being spilled into the water or
something like that, accidents happen.
What are the safety protocols that are
put into place for them?
I will say in all of the years,
as far As for cannabis,
while we did have various complaints and
other items,
they would generally be resolved fairly
quickly and readily.
There were situations and issues where,
for example,
we would go in on a site inspection and
discover that, quite frankly,
pounds and pounds of cannabis that had
mold or mildew on them.
And those of course need to be destroyed.
And there were arguments of no,
we're not going to destroy it,
we're going to remediate it when it
wasn't necessarily possible.
So those are the kinds of things they
don't necessarily see the same sort of
issues with regard to psilocybin
mushrooms,
but it still needs to be there as a in
case because there could also be
situations we never would have thought up.
And so we do need to have that there.
You know, the anticipation of course,
is that the people involved are all going
to be good actors,
but you never know when potential bad
actors enter into the press.
And so that's what we need to be cautious
about and that's really what this section
is about.
We want to ensure that people understand
we are looking at this from a safety
perspective.
And again, as I mentioned before,
for if there are minor things,
small things that are going on that need
to be corrected,
there is that other action that would
happen long before any of this where the
permittee would have 30 days to correct
whatever potential issue there was.
This is really,
if there's something that is so egregious
that it really is an immediate potential
health and safety issue or again,
if it was ongoing and not being correct.
And so that's when this would come into
play,
not in the situation where there was some
minor infraction or some minor not
following the law forgot to enter
something into the system that's going to
be required for trick tracking product.
And so as long as that gets corrected and
amended within that 30 day.
We move forward.
But if, for example,
there are other issues,
one of the other ones that is outlined in
this is, for example,
say we had a producer who was then
selling and selling through illegal
methods or or selling illegally illicitly
to other individuals or selling across
state lines.
Those are things that are not allowed and
not permitted.
Those could be other reason for immediate
suspension and for this process to then
come up.
I hope that helps.
James,
did I catch what you're trying to sort of
get at or do you need to clarify or do I
need to clarify a little more?
I think your mic's enabled,
so you should be able to unmute if any.
Don, that definitely answered it.
But one more thing to follow up is,
and I'm with you,
I think everybody that's going to be
dealing with is very professional.
But if I just want to make sure that the
language here is because these type of
claims can be,
they're going to be very serious and and
people in the world community are going
to be, I frankly, Don, a little scared.
This is going to be a pretty big process
and it should be because these claims are
very serious to take.
I mean,
I just want to make sure that those
people are also seen as innocent until
proven otherwise even, you know?
And so I want to make sure that the
origination of these type of sightings
issuings would only be given on the
proven ground that that is actually
occurring.
And that's all I was just trying to say.
Thank you.
Sure.
And thank you, James.
I do appreciate it.
And that's why, as I mentioned,
there's that part of the process that
happens before where there's that
opportunity to correct issues and all of
that sort of, you know,
aspect of it is actually also in place
because we want to ensure that everybody,
you know, people make mistakes.
There are accidents happen.
This is not about those sort of things.
This is about when people are
deliberately and egregiously doing things
that are potentially going to be harmful
or outright illicit with in regard to the
Medical Psilocybin Act.
So completely understand that though,
and we got Denali.
I just a couple of things.
I wanted to 2nd Gregory's recommendation
for an emergency hearing,
especially because I've recommended an
extension for the permittee's benefit of
having more time to file a review that
just adds more time to the,
the full timeline.
I'm not familiar with that emergency
clause in the cannabis regulations,
but certainly agree that and,
and you know,
hearings are really expensive for the
department to conduct.
We really want to be and devising
compliance and remediation around every
corner.
And so at every point where we can remind
people that remediatory evidence should
be submitted as a part of this process,
I'd like to make that recommendation.
And I imagine that that's a part of the
emergency hearing provisions as well.
And then on the the final section,
this is really where my earlier comment
about the term appellant comes in.
So I'm curious and maybe this is a
question for legal.
I'm I'm not sure or maybe it's a question
for somebody in the room that has
experience in, in with the cannabis board.
I'm not sure whether there is a statutory
right to appeal if if there is it that is
already set out in how to appeal to a
District Court, right?
We're,
we're leaving the administrative process
and we're appealing to a District Court
to have judicial review of the process.
And I, I would just say that if it,
if there isn't already a statutory right
to review,
I think there needs to be a provision
setting up what the review to District
Court is.
It's just a really incredibly important
due process protection that there is some
way for after a final decision,
whether it's already protected in statute,
I'm not sure.
Or if not, you know,
we set it up in in the rules and
regulations and make sure that somebody
has a way for District Court review.
Yeah.
And just as a note,
that is something that if, for example,
if there was a revocation that occurred
and the secretary's decision came out,
they would still of course be available.
Those other legal options would be able,
I think I,
I want them to be and they're only,
they're only available if there's a
statutory right to review or if it's in
the rule.
And that's the question that I have.
I'm not sure if it would be in the
Medical Psilocybin Act that we create a
right to review for permittees.
But if we didn't create it,
then we need to create it and rule now
because otherwise it's actually not
available unless there's a constitutional
violation and there's just I mean there
there's speech and religious access.
I can see that may be coming up,
but that's going to be really extreme
cases.
Thank you, Denali, I'll pass it on.
And just as a note,
as far as all of the dates with regard to
how long the process takes,
one thing to note is that is in in all
the cases of the day that's no later then.
So if it could be a speedier review,
if that's occurring.
So that's actually where that part comes
in as far as with regard to how fast the
process takes.
But yes, if for example,
everybody who's involved in it,
it's the longest possible time frame of
it.
Yes,
this can take several months for this
process.
However,
if again they take the shorter time frame
and make sure that they submit items on
in a timely fashion and all of that,
it can take so that then it effects.
And this is where Denali's point earlier
was a good one of if they need to obtain
legal counsel.
I mean, if that it may take longer.
Greg's got his hand up.
I'm going to localize it.
I'll speak into the micro.
Yeah, sorry about that.
If there were any way to add options to
opt in for electronic communications,
I would love to not have to get mad.
We're a part of the program.
I don't know if that's a possibility,
but I'm sure you haven't answered.
Yeah.
So the reason why it's there specifically
for the US Postal Service is, again,
because that's what we have to do for
legal notices,
that aspect of it to ensure delivery and
why it's also certified.
However, that does not mean,
and we're already putting the plans in,
that as a system goes into play,
that there will be electronic notices as
well.
But again,
we can't just do it through e-mail
because there's too much where people can
actually say, I never got that.
It went to my spam, it went to my junk,
it automatically got filtered out,
all that sort of thing.
So we will have both options,
but from a legal standpoint,
we have to have that US post.
Right,
Greg and I are just bouncing off each
other.
I'm going to recommend maybe this is
Denali, I am going to recommend.
So where we have certified mail,
maybe say and,
or and other reasonable means that is a
way to capture that we are making all
attempts to make contact,
especially with people who may have PO
boxes that are, you know,
I don't know if you're running a business,
you go to the post office maybe once a
week and that is cutting into your time
to respond.
So I'll come up with better language
recommendation,
but I think we can just add it to the end.
Yes,
we're issuing to a permittee via
certified US mail and reasonable other
reasonable means of communication.
Do we have other comments or questions,
anything online?
Yeah, OK.
And then and then Denali,
it's good having a meeting with you.
Thank you for everything you do.
I just wanted some clarity on where
corrective action protocols are going to
be written and defined and what part of
the process that like book is going to be
because that's clearly not for this
section, but it's integral.
It'll actually be the sections right
before this and that's where it'll
outline.
These are the things that happen.
There's a notice of contemplated action.
These are the things you need to correct.
And with that timeline and all of that,
there an outline in that in that section.
Other questions James Brown just says I'm
in favor of the addition of electronic
submissions as well if possible.
I actually wanted to this is Denali again,
I wanted to return to something that we
discussed last meeting,
but I don't know if that's appropriate at
this time or if I should wait.
No, go right on ahead.
And I know that I, I've shared,
I shared concerns last week with of
around the requirements for demonstrating
either ownership of the premises or
having written permission from the
landlord.
I haven't really figured out the best way
to make a recommendation for a,
an amendment there.
I,
I just continue to be really concerned
that we're going to disproportionately
prejudice folks who do not own the place
where they're doing business.
It seems very unlikely that renters,
even landlords who want to be supportive
of the industry will, will sign that.
So I,
I actually am just curious if maybe folks
who are already in mycology were in the
room.
And if you are a renter especially,
I think it would be helpful for us to
maybe have a conversation either as a
part of this meeting,
if that is acceptable to the chairing
department or, you know,
after the meeting concludes to talk about
what your renting situation is now and
what your landlords may be willing or not
willing to do as it comes to that
provision.
We have time for discussion now.
So if anybody would like to talk about
that, bring attention to that.
Let's go ahead.
I think several of our mycologists have
not showed up to this meeting.
I'm not seeing a lot of the normal usual
suspect on.
I just want to say that I grow mushrooms
and I own my own property and I'm
actually just bought a second property
and I'm developing it for a new facility
and that's why I'm here to make sure that
I'm developing it correct.
In case you have any special rules.
Oh, and what's your name again?
Oh,
Stephanie Duquette with Santa Fe Mountain
Measures.
Thanks.
So I actually own all my property as well
and my ownership to my business is
actually being transferred over to me.
So I,
if anything happens with my business
partner, he's just concerned.
He's a elderly gentleman,
he's just concerned with his health.
So if anything ever,
if he ever randomly kicks the bucket,
it's a smooth transition for me.
But I've been doing this since the end of
2016 and I've found from I was originally
doing an A rental home,
I didn't speak with my renters when I did
it in my rental home.
I just kind of did it.
I just made sure nothing was leaking
anywhere really was making sure I wasn't
causing any physical damage to the
buildings.
I wouldn't know how to address that as a
renter now,
just because I do know that mycology can
lead to a lot of damage if you're not
doing the property.
What's your name?
My name is Zachary Clark.
Thanks.
Right.
And James put in the James Brown put in
the comments.
If the Department of Health is unable to
deliver or conduct the inspections,
what are the next steps in the process?
Is there wording to that already?
Thank you, James.
It's a requirement that from our
standpoint that we're going to have to
conduct those inspections.
If for some reason, for example,
when we had COVID occurred,
we figured out ways to do it,
including through electronic means where,
for example,
when inspections would happen,
people that were there had to actually
show on their electronic device with
video and they had to actually direct the
cameras into all of the areas that were
requested.
Obviously not ideal.
And that was a very interesting situation
to say the least.
But there are other potential methods
sometimes that can be utilized.
But that is a part of what we will be
doing as part of the program is doing
those inspections to ensure that agencies
or that permittees are within compliance.
But it's a great question.
You know, what would happen, for example,
if our entire staff won the lottery and
we suddenly didn't have anyone to do it,
that we would have to move forward with
that.
And there will be down the road some
additional regulations that will be
implemented or that will be reviewed and
brought up that will actually address
some of those kind of potential long shot
but emergency type situations.
Oh, and actually real quick,
before we go to Denali,
Hana Rose has her hand up online.
Hana,
your mic should be enabled if you want to
unmute.
Thank you.
Yeah,
I just wanted to speak to what Denali
brought up because this ties into like
equity,
an equity issue like that and and like
accessibility and inclusion.
Because if if,
if her projection you know is correct
that like a lot of landlords will be
hesitant on signing off on this.
Then that really limits everyone to being
land owners,
which is a highly privileged position.
And so guess I just wanted to thank
Denali for speaking to this.
And some ideas that I have are, you know,
like program like incentives for
landlords to sign off on this or
incentives for land owners to support
other people that aren't land owners in
this process.
You know,
I'm just coming from that that social
work perspective of, of diversity,
equity and inclusion.
So those are just my curiosities and I
just wanted to share that.
Thank you.
A similar equity question.
I'm so sorry.
We were actually muted for a hot second
online.
So no one.
Yeah, after the online comment,
we didn't hear anything.
So if someone was speaking,
can you please repeat yourself?
My apologies.
I can, and I'm sorry.
Even better this time I was just
expressing gratitude and recommended that
we continue to have this conversation
ahead of the April 24th public hearing.
If you can come together with a
recommendation to the department and I
requested that Hannah,
you share your contact information in the
chat and I get it from the department
staff here in the room.
I think this is that there's a related
issue as people were sharing it sounds
like we have a lot of home,
home based growers of people who are
selling farmers markets now.
I mean this is,
this is the industry that we're talking
about incorporating in here.
And I, so the,
the related equity question that I have
that I think is,
is very connected to this ownership
question is whether we are going to allow
residential residentially zoned places of
business or if we will require them to be
commercial because they're I mean owning
your home is, is an equity issue.
And then separately, right,
owning a business property that that's a
whole different issue.
So I,
I don't know if that question is for the
department or if it's for another
committee, but that's my question.
So earlier the process we made the
recommendation that and that all
businesses had to be licensed and zoned
appropriately per the municipality.
So it's going to be up to your local
regulations of where that business.
Still Gregory,
I fit into the category of home ecologist.
I don't have any visions of providing
like producer,
like I'm not going to do that.
I believe strongly that this program
needs to stand up and be effective for a
period of time to create normalization in
our society.
And then hopefully that creates a world
that opens up boutique markets doing
specialized mycology in a variety of
settings possible.
That's my personal view on the issue.
But I think that we really need to be
pretty like hard lined about what we
produce for the medical program.
I think a lot of people see a
relationship between like medical
cannabis, but it's not that.
Like,
there's no strip mall doctor that gives
you a script for 100 bucks and then you
meet somebody in and out.
It's not what this is.
And I think the context needs to be
respected.
And we all need to be patient and like,
we're gonna change the world,
but we have to do it incrementally.
Thank you, Greg.
Any other comments?
Just real quick online from James Brown.
Thank you, Chris.
The Advisory Board members and the
department for the in person of virtual
meetings.
We all appreciate what you're doing for
the program and we have a little more
time if anybody wants to discuss any
other aspects of the program.
So I'm not sure if the Advisory Board is
going to have more work for the
propagation committee,
and we don't have any more of these
meetings scheduled.
So this might be a bittersweet ending to
that.
The propagation committee, I'm not sure.
But if we do have more meetings in the
future,
I'm looking forward to working with you
all again.
But I'll be in the other committees and
just grateful for all your support and
all of you coming into this space and
bringing your voices in to help make this
a great program.
So thank you.
Awesome.
And this is just a reminder for if you
want to submit a public comment to go
ahead and send that to the medical.
psilocybin@doh.nm.gov.
Yay.
I got it right.
Yeah.
And again, I'll say it again.
Well, I'll put it in the chat.
That's what I'll do.
We don't.
We don't need to hear that again.
That was Johnny Mouchet talking,
by the way, for the minutes.
Oh, yes, she did.
All right,
if there's no other comments in person,
can we give us a round of applause?
Yeah, So let's give Chris.
Let's let's see a round of applause.
Thank you, Chris.
Right.
Chris, are you going to do adjourn?
Right.
We are ending the meeting.
Thank you everybody.